Роздоріжжя у майбутнє
Життєві обставини
Many Future Paths!!
The Circumstances Everyone Bears
Я йду від тебе.
I'm breaking up with you.
Я більше не можу зустрічатись з тобою!
I can't go out with someone like you anymore!
Йде...
Breaking up...
Хто?
Who is?
Я?
I am?
Отані і я розлучаємось?
Otani and I are breaking up?
Аййй!
Owww!
Саме через таке ти набридла Отані!
Stuff like that is the very reason Otani is fed up with you!
Відверто, про що ти думала, гуляючи з іншим
Honestly, what the heck were you thinking, leaving your studying boyfriend behind
за спиною свого хлопця?
and going out with another guy at the drop of a hat?
Все не так...
It wasn't like that...
Що? Моє припущення невірне?
What? Was my account inaccurate?
Ні...
No...
Нобу! Що мені робити?
Nobu-chan! What should I do?
Не моє діло. Прийми наслідки.
I don't care. You reap what you sow.
Розберись сама.
Figure it out yourself.
Твоя правда.
I guess you're right.
Все буде добре, Рісо.
It'll be all right. Risa-chan.
Вибачайся і він пробачить.
If you keep apologizing,
I'm sure he'll forgive you.
Я не хотіла йому зраджувати, але
I didn't mean to cheat on him, but...
того справді не варто було робити.
that really was the wrong thing to do.
Має ж бути границя моїй дурості.
There should be a limit to my stupidity.
Отані!
Otani!
Отані, пробач.
Otani, I'm sorry.
За що?
What for?
Пробач, що гуляла з іншим.
I'm sorry for going out with that other guy.
Я так більше не буду.
I'm not going to do anything that stupid ever again.
Добре.
It's fine.
Гуляй скільки заманеться. Це мене не стосується.
You can go out as much you want. It's got nothing to do with me.
Гей! Зажди!
Hey! Wait!
Не кажи так!
Don't say that!
Чого тобі?
What's your problem?
Мені шкода!
I'm really sorry!
Не поривай зі мною!
Please don't break up with me!
Заціпся. Чоловік тримається слова.
Shut up! A man never goes back on his word.
Не кажи так.
Don't say that!
Не грай з себе мачо.
There s no need to act all macho now!
Це ж все твоя провина.
This only happened because you did something you shouldn't have, right?
Тому я й вибачаюсь!
That's why I'm apologizing!
Деякі речі так не виправиш.
There are things that can be fixed with an apology, and things that can't.
Що ти тоді хочеш?
Then what do you want me to do?
Роби що заманеться.
Do whatever you want.
Тепер ми чужі.
You're a stranger to me from now on.
Отані!
Otani!
Зажди, Отані!
Wait, Otani!
Не може...
No way...
Бути...
This can't be happening...
Це погано.
This is bad.
Кінець.
The end.
Не вірю.
I can't believe it.
Неможливо...
Це ж сон, так?
This can't be happening...
This is all a dream, right?
Просто поганий сон.
This is just a bad dream.
Минуло багато часу відтоді.
Its been a while since that last happened...
Ай.
Ouch.
Це не сон.
This isn't a dream.
Ти у порядку?
Are you okay?
Так. Порядок.
Yeah, I'm fine.
Я допоможу.
I'll help out.
Дякую.
Thank you.
Я думаю, це кінець.
I guess it's really over, huh?
Коїзумі, пробач за такі злі слова.
Koizumi, I'm sorry I said such cruel things.
Що це?
What's that?
Голос твого серця.
The whispering of your heart.
Ви мене для цього покликали?!
Is that what you asked me to come here for?!
Я йду! В мене є справи.
I'm going home! I'm busy.
І що робитимеш?
So what are you planning to do?
З чим?
About what?
Справді розійдетесь?
You're really going to break up?
Звісно.
Of course.
Надовго?
For how long?
Га?!
Huh?!
У сенсі надовго?
What do you mean, "for how long"?
Остаточно!
For good!
НазавШе!
FOLEVER!
Помилка.
That's wrong.
Назавже.
Forever.
Щось поганеньке майбуття.
Your future doesn't look good.
Тому ми й рвемо.
That's why I'm breaking up with her.
Думки про неї не дають зосередитись.
I worry about her so much that I can't concentrate on my studies.
От дурепа...
That idiot...
Навіть якщо розійдетесь, хіба не думатимеш далі?
Even if you break up, won't you still worry about her?
Взагалі! Тепер мені все рівно!
Not at all! I don't care anymore!
Яке полегшення!
I'm totally relaxed!
Он як...
Is that so...
Не думала, що він такий упертий.
I didn't think he was that stubborn.
Що поробиш. Це моя провина.
It can't be helped. It was all my fault.
До того ж зараз важливий час.
Besides, this is an important time for him.
Не маю його тривожити.
I shouldn't bother him anymore.
Ти все облишиш отак?
Don't tell me you're just going to leave it like this?
Вибач, що потурбувала.
Sorry for worrying you.
Що кажеш?
What are you saying?
Ти допомогла мені з Хоккайдо.
You're the one who helped me with the Hokkaido problem.
Я хочу віддячити.
I want to help you too.
Дякую, але все добре. Це наша справа.
Thanks, but it's okay. Things are already over between us.
Рісо!
Risa!
Забула віддати це йому.
I forgot to give this to him.
Я ж зробила це, то можу й віддати, вірно?
I took the time to make it, so it's still okay to give it to him, right?
Отані, постарайся.
Otani, do your best.
Агов, що таке?
Hey, what's the matter?
Га?
Oh?
Ачику, ось.
A-chan, here.
Га?
Huh?
Ацуші Отані
Otani Atsushi
Га?
Huh?
Пане Ацуші Отані, я підтримую вас у підготовці до тестів.
Otani Atsushi-sama, I support you in your test efforts.
Коїзумі Ріса.
Koizumi Risa.
О, це від Ріси.
Oh, it's from Risa-chan.
Не відкривай!
Don't just open it!
Як мило! Виглядає теплим.
How nice! It looks really warm.
Вдягни, Ачику.
Put it on, A-chan.
Постарайся! Уперед!
Do your best! Fight!
Ого! Як мило!
Wow! How cute!
Отані назавжди!
PASS! OTANI FOR LIFE!
Старе взяла?
Recycled, huh?
Ріса така хороша.
Risa-chan sure is a nice girl.
Чому вона не завітала?
But why didn't she come in?
Цікаво, чи прийняв Отані мій подарунок?
I wonder if Otani accepted my support goods?
Коїзумі, вже йдеш?
Koizumi-san, are you getting off now?
Так. А в тебе ще зміна, Кохорі?
Yeah. You're still working, Kohori-kun?
Так.
Yeah.
Бос питала чи ти вільна у грудні.
Oh, the boss asked for your availability for December.
Я забула!
Oh, I forgot!
Грудень...
December...
Різдво...
Christmas...
Цього року я буду однісінька...
I'm going to be all alone this year...
Коїдзумі, хочеш прийти на роботу напередодні Різдва?
Koizumi-san, do you want to come in to work on Christmas Eve?
Ми всі збираємося разом і влаштуємо вечірку після закриття.
We're all going to get together and have a party after we close.
Прийдеш, Коїзумі?
Would you like to come too, Koizumi-san?
Усі?
Everyone is?
Так.
Yeah.
Пані Мацубара теж.
Matsubara-san will be there too.
Чув того року стара напилася й так шаленіла.
I heard that the old lady got really drunk last year and went completely wild.
Та ну! Реально?
No way! Are you serious?!
Хочеш побачити?
Don't you want to see that?
Кохорі?
Kohori-kun?
Хто тут стара?
What's this about "the old lady"?
А ніхто!
Uh... nothing at all!
Я виношу сміття.
I'm taking out the trash.
Гарного дня!
Keep up the good work!
Коїзумі вже пішла.
If you re looking for Koizumi-san, she already left.
Що? А, ні...
What? Uh, no...
Просто йду на підготовку.
I was just on my way home from prep school.
Авжеж.
Of course you are.
Ви ж розійшлися...
You guys already broke up, after all...
А ти низенький. Який зріст?
You really are short. How tall are you?
Сто п'ятдесят вісім сантиметрів.
I'm 158cm.
Га? Неможливо! Я нижчий на 2 см?
Huh? No way! I'm 2cm shorter than you?
Ай! Ти що робиш?
Oww! What did you do that for?!
Не прикидуйся. Це твоя вина!
Don't play dumb with me. This is all your fault!
Накинувся на сплячу Коїзумі.
Attacking Koizumi while she was asleep...
Тільки тому, що вона була такою гарною, коли спала...
It was only because she looked so beautiful while she was sleeping...
Трясця! Не верзи таке соромітництво так голосно!
Good Lord! Don't say something so embarrassing out loud!
Це не соромно! Це правда!
It's not embarrassing! It's true!
Стулися! Мовчи, карлику!
Shut up! Cram it, you midget!
Я вищий на два сантиметри!
I'm 2cm taller than you, aren't I?!
І що?! Чого ти хочеш від Коїзумі?
So what?! And besides, just what do you want with Koizumi?!
Вона мені подобається.
I like her.
Я більше не стримуватимусь.
I'm not going to hold back anymore.
Н А З А
F O R E
Н А З А В
F O R E V
Назавжди.
Forever.
Цікаво, що він зробив з халатом?
I wonder what he did with the coat?
Це не має значення. Поки він робить усе можливе.
Well, it doesn't matter. As long as he does his best.
Різдво з Отані...
A Christmas without Otani...
Я Коїзумі Ріса, співатиму пісню Умібозу!
I'm Koizumi Risa, and I'll be singing an Umibouzu song!
Що поробиш. Що поробиш.
Can't be helped~ Can't be helped~
Я в порядку.
I'm okay.
Все буде добре.
I'm going to be fine.
Бачиш? Мені весело.
See? I'm having fun.
Зазвичай на цьому місці Отані підхоплював.
This is where Otani would usually break in and interject.
І кричав "Так" з дурним лицем.
He'd always make a silly face and shout "Yeah!" right around here.
Хочу побачити...
I want to see him...
Побачити його.
I really want to see him.
Ачику, шматочок пирога?
A-chan, want some Christmas cake?
Га?
Huh?
Виглядаєш втомленим.
You look really tired.
Тобі слід відпочивати.
You should take a break once in a while, you know.
Ага...
Uh uh...
Різдво все-таки. Чому б не зустрітися з Рісою?
It is Christmas, after all. Why don't you spend it with Risa-chan?
Думаєш?
You think?
Так.
Yeah.
Бачила її біля станції. Стояла з хлопцем твого зросту.
I saw her near the station not long ago. She was with a boy around your height.
Я більше не стримуватимусь.
I'm not going to hold back anymore.
Коїзумі!
Koizumi-san!
Ачику!
A-chan!
Думала, що зможу побути без Отані,
I thought I could go on being normal without Otani,
але це не так!
but I just can't!
Я просто...
I'm just...
Обережно!
That's dangerous!
Боляче мабуть.
That looked painful.
Вона ціла?
Is she all right?
Аййй.
Owww...
Мені погано без Отані.
I'm just no good without Otani.
Отані. Чому?
Otani... Why?
Ти надто часто падаєш, як для свого зросту.
You sure fall over a lot for someone with such a big body.
Халат...
That coat...
Так.
Yeah...
Не певен, щодо поношеного, але дякую.
I'm not too sure about the recycled aspect of it, but thanks.
Після екзаменів, я знову покличу тебе гуляти.
Once you finish with your exams, I'm going to ask you out again.
Я наполеглива, сам знаєш.
I'm persistent, you know.
Навіть якщо кинеш мене чи скажеш щось, я не здамся.
Even if you dump me, or say you're breaking  up with me, I'm not going to give up.
Тож зосередся на іспитах.
So just focus on the entrance exams for now.
Отані...
O-Otani...
Пробач.
Sorry.
Пробач за мої слова.
Forget that I said we'd break up.
Забираю назад.
I take it back.
Але ж, іспити...
B-But... your exams...
Йой. Погано.
Oh no. This is bod.
Що?
What?
Схоже, ти мені подобаєшся більше, ніж я думав.
I... I seem to like you more than I realized.
Що...
No way...
Що за звуки.
Don't make weird noises.
Якщо ти казатимеш такі речі,
If you're going to say something that nice to me,
я не проти порвати сотню разів.
I don't mind if we break up a hundred times.
Отані...
Otani...
Що?
What is it?
Усі вирячаються.
Everyone is staring at us.
Я знаю!
I know that!
Твоє лице не видно, а моє усі бачать.
Your face might be hidden,
but everyone can see mine.
Дурепо. А у мене на спині напис "постарайся".
Idiot. I've got "do your best"
written on my back, don't I?
Але ти справді маєш...
You really should do your best...
Побігли.
Let's make a run for it.
Добре.
Okay.
Один, два.
1...2...
О. У мене немає подарунку для тебе.
Oh... I didn't get you a Christmas present.
Ти вже подарував.
But you already gave me something.
Що? Я ж нічого не давав.
Huh? I didn't give you anything.
Дещо чудове.
It was something wonderful.
Схоже, ти мені подобаєшся більше, ніж я думав.
I seem to like you more than I realized.
Це був найкращий подарунок у житті.
That was the best present ever.
Нічого більше не треба.
I don't need anything else.
Ось так ми подолали ту безпрецедентну кризу і увійшли в новий рік.
And so, we overcame that unprecedented crisis and entered the new year.
Погано!
This is bad!
Новий Рік, а ми спізнюємось!
It's New Years Day, and we're already late!
Я проспав, бо ти подзвонила мені уранці!
I only slept in because you called and woke me up at some odd hour!
Якби я цього не зробила, ти б засмутився.
You'd be sad if I hadn't, though.
Хто сказав?!
Who says?!
Ви як завжди спізнюєтесь.
You guys are both late, as always.
Отже, наша мила парочка на місці.
Okay, everyone, the lovey-dovey couple is here.
Вітаємо з примиренням.
Congratulations on getting back together.
Мій шанс...
I thought this was my chance...
Помолюся за їх новий розрив.
I'm going to pray for them to break up again.
Харука як зажди за своє...
Haruka-senpai is being petty as always...
Отані та інші почали серйозно готуватися,
Otani and the others started seriously getting into pre-exam study,
а Нобу і я молилися за їх успіх.
and Nobu-chan and I prayed for them from the sidelines.
Час покупок!
Time to hit the sales!
Нобу, це чудово пасуватиме до нової спідниці.
Nobu-chan, this'll go really well with that skirt you bought last time.
Який класний!
Oh, this is great!
Інші так стараються. Чи нормально нам веселитись?
Everyone else is working so hard. Is it okay for us to be doing stuff like this?
Не "нам". Ти єдина не визначилась з майбутнім.
Not "us". You're the only one who still hasn't decided on your future plans.
На що вступатимеш?
What course are you going to take at technical college?
Такий великий вибір...
Well, there are so many...
Отані йде на вчителя, то може мені на виховательку в садочку?
Say, if Otani is going to be a teacher, how about I become a kindergarten teacher?
Туди теж іспити.
You'll need to take an exam to get into a college specializing in early childhood education.
Жартуєш!
You're kidding!
Як щодо дизайну? В тебе є чуття стилю.
Say, what about going into fashion design? You've got a good sense of style.
Ну, я люблю виглядати гарно, але це ж інше.
Well, I do like looking nice... but this and that are...
Милий, я вже йду.
Ah, Darling, I m on my way now.
Так. Побачимось.
Sure. See you.
Чіхару?
Chiharu-chan?
Сузукі?
Suzuki-kun?
Га?!
Huh?!
Сузукі провалив тест?
The Center Test is an annual standardized test offered throughout Japan and is used by many universities to determine admission.
Suzuki-kun failed the Center Test?
Ви не зможете вступити в один університет!
Then you and Chiharu-chan won't be able to go to the same school!
Все через хворобу.
I was sick the day of the exam.
Ти в порядку?
Are you all right?
В порядку. Я...
I'm fine. I... I'm...
Прийняв надто багато пігулок і не міг нічого пригадати.
He took too much cold medicine and couldn't remember anything from about halfway through.
Це означає...
So... that means...
Ми не зможемо вступити в одне місце.
We can't go to the same school.
Вибач, що не дотримався обіцянки.
I'm sorry for breaking my promise.
Обіцянки?
Promise?
Зажди! Сузукі!
Wait! Suzuki-kun!
Дай йому час.
Leave him alone for now.
Що за обіцянка?
What was the promise?
Минулого року ми пішли на фестиваль від університету.
Well, last year we decided to visit a University and went to their festival...
Сузукі, де ти?
Suzuki-kun, where are you?
Яка кралечка.
Oh, what a cute girl.
Повеселимось? З якого ти курсу?
Wanna come have some fun with us? What year are you in?
Я старшокласниця.
Umm... I'm still a high school senior.
Вступатимеш сюди?
So are you going to apply here next year?
Було б чудово, якби така мила дівчина, як ти, вступила до нас.
It'd be great having a cute girl like you come to our school.
Танако!
Tanaka-san!
Сузукі!
Suzuki-kun!
Що? Вже є хлопець?
What? She s already got a guy?
Погано.
Too bad.
Універ страшний.
University is scary.
Багато багато хлопців...
Lots and lots of guys came...
Танако...
Tanaka-san...
Багато... Так багато...
So many... There were so many...
Хто... Хто я?
Who... Who am I?
Все добре.
You'll be all right.
Я завжди буду поруч, Танако.
I'll always be by your side, Tanaka-san.
Сузукі...
Suzuki-kun...
Он воно як.
So that's what happened.
Що мені робити?
What do you think I should do?
Чіхару...
Chiharu-chan...
Сузукі...
Suzuki-kun...
Я збираюсь вступати туди, куди й ти, тому старайся, добре?
I'm going to go to whichever school you go to, so do your best, okay?
Знаю, знаю...
I know, I know...
Що?
What?
Не допетрав?
Don't you get it?
Що?
Get what?
Ти не підеш туди, куди проходиш?
So you're going to give up on your first choice school?
Так. Хочу бути з тобою, Сузукі.
Yes. I want to be with you, Suzuki-kun.
Я не певен.
I'm not confident.
Га?
Huh?
Навіть якщо ти зміниш свій вибір
Even if you lower yourself to my level and change your first-choice university,
не певен чи зможу вступити кудись.
I don't know if I can get in anywhere.
Що?!
What?!
Ти про що, Сузукі?!
What are you saying, Suzuki-kun?!
Коли Чіхару теж бажає...
When Chiharu-chan is willing too...
Чому? Чому ти таке говориш?
Why? Why would you say such a thing?
Я не виконав свою обіцянку.
I couldn't keep our promise.
Певен, є багато інших хлопців, які могли б захистити тебе в університеті замість мене.
I'm sure there are plenty of other guys who could protect you at university in my place.
Танако!
T-Tanaka-san!
Чіхару, обережно.
Ch-Chiharu-chan, that's dangerou-
Замовкли усі!
Be quiet!
Так!
Yes!
Я хочу в один університет не через твій захист!
I don't want to go to the same school just so you can protect me!
А тому що хочу бути разом!
I want to be with you!
Танако.
Tanaka-san...
Кажеш замінити тебе.
And yet, you say I can replace you...
Чіхару!
Chiharu-chan!
Кажеш, що не певен.
Saying you re not confident...
Сузукі, ти дурень!
Suzuki-kun, you're an idiot!
Чіхару.
Ch-Chiharu-chan...
Ото розлютилася.
She got pretty angry, huh?
І засмутилася.
She was really upset...
Що робитимеш?
What are you going to do?
У сенсі?
What do you mean?
Чому все так?
Просто підіть в один заклад.
Why does it have to be like that?
Can't you two just go to the same school?
Це для її ж добра і для мого.
It's for her own good, and for my good too.
Бачу. Та книга.
Oh, I see it. That book.
Дякую.
Thank you.
У тому університеті є викладач літератури, якого поважає Танака.
There's a literature professor who Tanaka-san really respects teaching at that university.
То ж не дати їй туди вступити через мене...
So to give up her first-choice school for my sake...
Думаю, з часом вона пошкодує, що не пішла туди.
I think when she works out what she really wants to do in the future, she'll regret not going there.
Он як.
I see.
Не хочу цього.
I don't want that to happen.
Отже, Сузукі, ти казав це навмисно?
So you said those things deliberately, Suzuki-kun?
Чому ти себе так поводив?
Why'd you try to act cool like that?
Це неправильний спосіб показати їй свою турботу.
That's completely the wrong way to show her you care about her.
Так! Чому б не сказати правду?
Yeah! Why not just tell her the truth?
Вона б була щасливішою.
She would've been much happier that way.
Поспіши.
Hurry up and go.
Сюди!
Up here!
Пробач.
I'm sorry.
Ти був таким уважним до мене.
You were being considerate of me to that extent...
Я цього не розуміла.
I never realized.
Танако...
Tanaka-san...
Так?
Yes?
Я готуватимусь і наступного року вступлю туди ж, куди й ти
I'm going to keep studying, and get into the same school as you next year,
тому, будь ласка, почекайте мене доти.
so please wait for me until then.
Звісно.
Of course.
Щасти, Чіхару, Сузукі.
Good for you, Chiharu-chan, Suzuki-kun.
Що таке? Ти постійно зітхаєш.
What's wrong? You've been sighing for a while now.
У чому сенс життя?
What's the meaning of life?
Що це таке?!
What was that?!
Я єдина досі не визначилась!
Well, I'm the only one who hasn't decided on anything!
Коїзумі...
Koizumi...
Ці двоє підштовхнули мене на думку, що час вирішувати?
After watching those two today, I realized I really need to decide now,
щоб мій вибір не примусив мене шкодувати у майбутньому.
so that when I work out what I really want to do in the future, I won't have any regrets.
Це вірно. Поворуши мізками.
That's right. Work that brain of yours.
А ти готуй свої до іспитів.
You'll need to get yours into gear too for your exam prep.
Час пролетів швидко, і вже завтра вступні іспити.
So time passed quickly, and now the entrance exams are already tomorrow.
Жах! Про що я взагалі думаю?
No good! What the heck am I thinking?!
Я вдома.
I'm home.
Геть!
Get out!
Га?
Huh?
Що?
Wh-What?
Будинок заражено вірусом п'ятого рівня.
This house has been infected by a level 5 virus.
Рівня...
Level...
Що коїться?! Відчиніть!
What the heck is going on?! Open up!
Грип.
It's influenza.
І не лише у мене.
It's not just me.
У твого батька й у сестри гарячка й вони теж хворі.
Your father and sister are both feverish and sick too.
Будинок у карантині.
This house is under quarantine.
Карантині?
Quarantine?
А я?!
But what about me?!
Завтра екзамен!
I have an exam tomorrow!
Ось.
Here.
Га?
Huh?
Швидше. Бери й тікай!
Hurry. Take that and flee!
Переночуй у друзів.
Go and stay at a healthy friend's house for the night.
Це божевілля!
This is crazy!
Отані, молюся за тебе.
Otani, I'm praying for you.
Гей, стоп. Завтра екзамен.
Hey, wait... I have an exam tomorrow.
За що мені це?
Why is this happening to me?
Який прикол!
You've got to be kidding!
Постарайся!
Do your best in the exams!
Час для випускного!
But it's already time for graduation!
Коїзумі, не час ридати.
Koizumi, this isn't the time to cry.
Ми спізнимось на випускний.
We're going to be late for graduation!
Зворушливий комплекс Звор Ком.
Lovely Complex~ LoveCom!
Фінал: Разом Назавжди!
Final Episode: Together Forever.
Разом Назавжди!
Together Forever!!
Не пропустіть!
Be sure to watch!